[Music]
Welcome to the busy central launch
edition for 2025 release wave 2.
Uh in this session I will try together
with my colleague Alexander Gladco to
show you how you can easily connect 99
with the service. So before we jumping
into demo and presenting how it can
work, I would like to emphasize these
business values with this integration.
Earlier you had to print all these forms
on a paper prepare forms and to send it
manually. Now you can save the time with
the seamless integration. You just need
to upload to upload sorry to submit 1099
forms directly from B central. You can
send them uh through email to your
vendor. So this really save a time
providing really great integration and
of course it reduce compliance cost. You
will not be late. You can check the
progress of all your submission. If
something is wrong you will be informed
on a time. So you can be really
compliant and you will not have any
problem with the future reporting of
1099s.
So how does it work in the future?
As I mentioned no manually printed 109
forms. So you do not need to order
preprinted forms to do it. What you need
to do is print on your uh standard uh
blank paper. That's it. So you do not
need to order preprinted forms. Then for
submitting only electronic 109 forms. So
we will not have an option as I said to
print and to submit them on a printed
way. So for Iris submission, if you're
cloud user, you will have fully A2A
integration with the Iris portal. For
on-prem users, you can create uh fire
files and manually download and upload
to the fire. And even if you're cloud
user, you have this option. But
definitely our suggestion is look this
video and you will see how seamless this
integration is. So please if you're a
cloud user use this integrated A2A
integration with IRS portal. So now this
is for IRS for sending to vendors you
will have 1089 substitutions forms. What
does it mean? You can create PDFs and
send it via email to vendors if you have
uh consent from them or you can print on
hard copies and send via mail. If you
are uh sending via email, keep in mind
you can protect uh both uh your and
vendor team. So it can be safely to send
them via email. And the future for 1086
form, we will deprecate this
functionality because you do not need
1089 1086 when you are uh deploying 1089
electronically. So this functionality
will be deprecated.
What is actually new? Because almost
everything what you see on this slide
this is something already exist. Only
this small piece of work were missing.
So now we have this E file direct to
Oris and it is officially available from
two uh 2000 release wave 2 but even we
updated uh last minor 26.5. So you can
switch and you can report from both
these versions. So now Sasha will show
you a full demo. Sasha. Alexander, I'm
going to show you how to file 1099s
forms electronically. First, you set up
the IRS forms feature. You set up the
vendors post purchase invoices and apply
payments to them. Then, you create 1099
form documents
and the total amount of payments for
each vendor will be calculated. You see
that amount on the 1099 form document
card.
verify the amount for each document and
release it.
The next step is to combine all the
release 1099 form documents and send
them to the IRS. Go to the page iris
transmissions, select the action create
iris transmission, specify the reporting
period and click okay.
Carefully check that all the payments
that you want to report to the IRS are
in this transmission and when you are
ready press send.
Business central will check if all the
necessary data is filled in correctly,
create the XML and send it to the IRS.
In case I returns errors,
you fix them
and you send the replacement
transmission.
Do it until your transmission will be
accepted. You can see all your previous
actions on the transmission history
page. Here you can see when the
transmission was sent to the IRS, its
type and status.
If you click on the unique transmission
ID field, you'll see what exactly was
sent to the IRS.
And if you want to know what IRS
returned for this transmission, you
select the action download
acknowledgement content. Open the XML
and inside you'll see its statuses and
errors if there are any.
Let's then assume that after your
transmission was successfully accepted
by the IRS, you want to correct the
amounts for some vendors. Open the 1099
document that you want to correct and
reopen it. But you cannot just do it.
You firstly need to allow the document
to be corrected.
Select the allow correction action and
reopen the document.
Correct the amount.
release the document and close this card
and the corresponding transmission line
will be marked for the correction.
When you send the correction to the IRS,
only the lines marked with needs
correction will be sent and finally
those lines will be marked as corrected.
That's it. Thank you.
>> Okay. Thank you Sasha for this great
demo. As you could see this is something
what we are covering full end to end
scenario. So now you can really use
application to application integration
with ARIS without any problem.
Everything is seamless. So you can track
progress and you can see all statuses of
all your submitted 1089s.
Before we close this session, I remind
you to look into all these links so you
can find all important information about
Business Central. Please do not forget
subscribe on our LinkedIn channel so you
can track all news about Business
Central. And not only this video, you
can find another videos on our YouTube
channel AKMSBC YouTube. Not only for
this for this uh edition, you can find
all of uh uh videos related to this
edition but from previous ones as well.
Thank you for watching this video.